Thimoty Barbieri

Milan, Lombardy, Italy



thimoty@thimoty.it



linkedin.com/in/thimoty

Summary

Thimoty Barbieri is a freelance IT consultant since 1999, consulting on software design and implementation, testing, IT project management, training for companies and universities, technical translations and legal expertise in litigations. Thimoty and his staff can be hired on a project basis, for teaching a course, or for continuing collaborations on a pre-arranged schedule.

Thimoty Barbieri receives his MSc in Computer Engineering at Politecnico di Milano, Italy, in 1999. In 2003 receives his PhD in Computer Engineering and Automation at Politecnico di Milano. He is now Contract Professor at University of Pavia, where he teaches Software Engineering. For fifteen years he has taught Computer Graphics as Contract Professor at Politecnico di Milano. Since 1991 he works as a freelance translator for international PR companies, technical companies and customers in the field of Graphic Arts, Telecommunications, and Electronics. Thimoty translates from English into Italian, and from Russian into Italian.

Thimoty holds certifications as Software Engineer from Google (GCP Architect and Developer), Oracle (Oracle Cloud Infrastructure Architect, OCE Java EE 6/OCP Java8), Mulesoft (Developer & Architect), Microsoft (MCP C#), IBM (Rhapsody 8), RedHat (Jboss Certified Developer), IFPUG Function Points, OMG, Project Management Institute (PMP and PMI-ACP Agile), TOGAF 9.1, MongoDB, and other leading software vendors.

Since 1998, Thimoty worked as a professional consultant for domestic and international companies: he has designed and realized several systems for customers such as banks, commercial and trade enterprises, governmental institutions and utility companies. Thimoty has taught Object Oriented Design, Project Management, and Programming in several domestic and international companies using Java / Java EE and open source technology.

Specialties: Software design, Software Engineering, Function Point Analysis, Java EE Development, SOA/SOAP/ REST/ESB Integration, UML Design, Java, Higher Education Teaching, Translation

Experience

TECH Owner

ITECH Engineering

Jul 1998 - Present (25 years 4 months)

Information Technology Consultancy, Technical Translations, Technical Training



Enterprise Architecture Senior Consultant

Cegeka

2012 - Present (11 years)

Consultancy for Enteprise Architecture implementations. IT Factory Processes, Guidelines, Enterprise Training on Strategic Technologies, Digital Transformation, Transition of Dev and Ops activities to the Cloud.

Design and Implementation of a Microservices High-Performance Architecture with: Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI), Spring Boot, Spring Cloud, Docker, Kubernetes, Kafka, Kafka Streaming, MongoDB

JBoss 7 Migration, Analysis Design & Implementation of Finance Applications with JEE 6, JBoss 7 for a leading institution in the field of Betting, Numerical Games, Online Games

Data Analysis on Market Data for a leading national bank, development of automated data analysis system on JBoss 7 with JEE6, JSF, JPA, CDI

Management of SCRUM teams for the agile development of financial vertical applications with JBoss 7, TDD, Arquillian, JSF, JPA

Big Data Analysis of Financial Market Trade Data using MongoDB, Python, MLLib, NumPy, Matplot

> Mulesoft Training Specialist

Infomentum

Jan 2019 - Present (4 years 10 months) Mulesoft Certified Trainer

Currently working on HyperAutomation, RPA topics, MuleSoft RPA, Composer, Salesforce Einstein Bots

Courses for which I am Certified Trainer:

- Getting Started with Anypoint Platform 4.x
- Developer Fundamentals Mule 4.x Level 1
- Integration Solutions Architectures
- Application Network Architectures
- Operations: RunTime Fabric
- Operations: API Management
- Operations: CloudHub / CloudHub 2.0
- Development: API Design
- Development: Production-Ready Development Practices (Lev2)
- Development: Production-Ready Integrations (Lev2)
- Arch: Hyperautomation with Salesforce and MuleSoft

YVAMAGATA Freelance Translator

Yamaqata Europe

Aug 2008 - Present (15 years 3 months)

Translations for Esko Graphics and Enfocus Software

Platforms Used: SDL Trados Studio 2011 Freelance, SDL Trados Suite Professional 2007, Kilgray MemoQ 6, Atril Deja Vu X 2 Workgroup Edition, Alchemy Catalyst 10

Freelance Translator

Esko

Jan 1991 - Present (32 years 10 months)

Technical Translations; Documentation; Marcom; Software Localization

Enterprise Architect

Sisal

Jun 2016 - Jun 2023 (7 years 1 month)

As Enterprise Architect, I am consulting the company in the following areas, in close cooperation with the CIO and CTO:

- Alignment of IT strategy and planning with company's business goals.
- Drive Adoption and Tailoring of TOGAF 9.1 Best Practices
- Optimization of information management through an understanding of evolving business needs and technology capabilities.
- Strategic responsibility for the company's software development activities,
- Promotion of shared methodology and software technologies to reduce costs and improve information flow.
- Ensure that projects do not duplicate functionality or diverge from each other and business and IT strategies.
- Work with solution architects to provide a consensus based enterprise solution that is scalable, adaptable and in synchronization with ever changing business needs.
- Direct involvement in the development of policies, standards and guidelines that direct the selection, development, implementation and use of Information Technology within the enterprise.
- Build employee knowledge and skills in specific areas of expertise, promoting seminars and teaching events

Oracle Training Specialist

Fudgelearn

Jan 2019 - Jan 2023 (4 years 1 month)

Oracle Training Specialist for Oracle Cloud Infrastructure (OCI), Oracle Cloud DevOps, Oracle Kubernetes Platforms (OKE) and Java Based Technologies, Oracle Spatial Database, Spatial&Graph, Oracle ADW Autonomous Database Autonomous Warehouse

Teacher CodeMaster

Talent Garden

Nov 2016 - Sep 2022 (5 years 11 months)

Trainer for Front-End Developers in the Codemaster Course with the following technologies: React.js, Babel, Webpack, Node.js, React Native, Immutable.js, WebSockets, Mocha, Chai. ECMAScript 6 -JavaScript ES 2015 Programming, Functional Programming.



Freelance Translator

C.P. GAUGER CO., INC.

Sep 2016 - Sep 2022 (6 years 1 month)

Technical Translations in the field of Mechanical Engineering, Medical Equipment.

Senior Consultant

ISO SISTEMI

Jul 2014 - Sep 2022 (8 years 3 months)

Consultancy and Training for SOA-based Architectures with SOAP/REST WS, Jax-WS, Jax-RS, JBoss Fuse, Apache Camel, Apache ActiveMQ, Mule ESB. Design and Training of several editions of a Basic and Advanced SOA Design & Implementation course.

Model-Based Systems Engineering, SysML Design, IBM Rhapsody, DOORS NG, Team Concert, Harmony Process, Real-Time System Design with Model Execution, Jazz Platform, DOORS 9.6.1 with Test Tool Tracker

Co

Contract Professor

Università di Pavia

Jan 2007 - Sep 2022 (15 years 9 months)

Contract Professor of Software Engineering at the Faculty of Computer and Industrial Engineering

Contract Professor of Coding at the Faculty of Business Management and Economics

Contract Professor of Software and Web Technologies at the Master Full Stack Software Development

Senior Consultant

Unione Italiana dei Ciechi ed Ipovedenti Regione Lombardia

Oct 2014 - Oct 2019 (5 years 1 month)

Consultancy for implementation of an OpenEDX eLearning platform; eLearning consultancy; content accessibility consultancy

Freelance Translator

Modiano IP Law

2006 - Dec 2018 (12 years)

Translation of patents from english into italian in the fields of Software Engineering, ITC, Telecommunications, Networking

Senior Consultant

Mascherpa Spa

Jan 1999 - Dec 2018 (20 years)

B2B Order Portal, Finance/Warehouse/Marketing Information System

■ Freelance Translator

SparklingLengua

Jan 2008 - Jan 2018 (10 years 1 month)

Translation and Localisation from English Into Italian

▲AC Senior Consultant

Altroconsumo

Jan 2008 - Jan 2018 (10 years 1 month)

UML/ICONIX methodology; UML-Based and Functional Analysis in Agile Processes.

Design and Implementation of a High Avalability Data Cache for a SOA, using MongoDB 3 on Azure MongoLab, Azure Web Services, ASP.NET Web Api, C# 5.0.

Data Analysis and Statistical Inference on Consumer Complaint data using R: assessing Goodness of Fit of parameter proportions on categorical data, to check fitness of a Company Performance Score algorithm (used 95% confidence intervals; chi-squared checks). Performed simulation of Score on sample data, presented study results with plots generated from R and comments.

Lead Technical Consultant, Tactical Applications Italy

RBC

Jun 2013 - Mar 2015 (1 year 10 months)

Application Analysis, Development, Technical Team Leading and Project Management for Tactical Applications Development using Ruby on Rails framework and Agile Methodologies (TDD, Lean, XP)

IT Instructor

Education Time Spa

May 2012 - May 2014 (2 years 1 month)

Instructor for IT Courses: Function Point Analysis, Software Engineering, Project Management for IT

Expertise Consultant

ISLegal

2007 - Mar 2014 (7 years)

Technical Expertise on Information Systems (Procurement, Design, Development) for Litigations

Contract Professor

Politecnico di Milano

Jan 1999 - Feb 2014 (15 years 2 months)

Professor of Computer Graphics

Java EE Senior Architect

FORMAT Systems & Networks S.r.l.

May 2012 - Dec 2013 (1 year 8 months)

SOA Integration, Requirements, Design and Implementation based on Java EE, JBoss 7, Oracle Spatial



Senior Consultant

Atos

Nov 2005 - Dec 2013 (8 years 2 months)

Web Energy Sales project, Miservi project, Energy Metering project

SOA Integration Architect

YouCo

Mar 2011 - Dec 2012 (1 year 10 months)

Design and Implementation of SOA-based integration of Web and Mobile solutions with ERP backends (SAP, BAAN, Oracle-based ERPs), using ESB, SOAP/REST technologies, JD Edwards Enterprise One BSSV Incapsulation with JD E1 Tools 8.98.

Senior Consultant J2EE

Format Systems & Networks Nov 2005 - May 2012 (6 years 7 months) J2EE Senior Architect

Partner

Ingenya Srl

Jan 2010 - Dec 2011 (2 years)

Software Engineering Company: ERPs, CRMs, J2EE Systems, Domotics, Mobile Apps

Software Metrics Consultant

Sidi S.r.I.

2008 - May 2011 (3 years)

Certification CFPS Training for Function Point Specialist Groups

Freelance Translator

duomedia

Jan 2005 - Sep 2010 (5 years 9 months)

Marcom for leading computer graphics companies

Senior Consultant

Opera21 SPA

Dec 2006 - May 2008 (1 year 6 months)

Logistics Information Systems

Senior Consultant

Comau

Sep 2007 - Dec 2007 (4 months)

Lecturer and Consultant for UML Real Time Modeling for Robotic Systems

Senior Consultant

Sopra Steria

Jan 2005 - Dec 2006 (2 years)

Customer J2EE Portal for Credite Agricole; Framework Development in J2EE

Senior Consultant

Intersistemi Italia S.P.A

2000 - 2002 (2 years)

J2EE Consultancy, Java over RMI Consultancy, Project Management Seminaries at European Space Agency (Tor Vergata)

Education

Politecnico di Milano

PhD, Computer Engineering and Automation

2000 - 2003

Collaborative Web Based Systems, Computer Graphics, Computer Security and Forensics, Assistive Technology for the Sensorial and Cognitively Impaired

Politecnico di Milano

MSc in Computer Engineering, Information Technology 1991 - 1999

Liceo Classico Carducci

Maturità Classica, Humanities, Classic Literature 1986 - 1991

Licenses & Certifications

American Translators Association Certified Translator EN>IT - American
Translators Association
518984

- PMP Project Management Professional Project Management Institute 1763891
- PMI-ACP Agile Certified Practitioner Project Management Institute 1812307
- TOGAF 9.1 Certified Enterprise Architect The Open Group
- JBCAA / RHCJA JBoss Certified Application Administrator EAP 6 Red Hat Issued Mar 2013 - Expires Oct 2017 130-051-600
- PSM-I Professional Scrum Master I Scrum.org
- CFPS 4.3.1 Certified Function Point Specialist IFPUG International Function Point User Group

- OMG-Certified Systems Modeling Professional SysML OMG OMG00017787
- IBM Certified Specialist Rhapsody for Systems V8 IBM IBM000102396
- MCPS: Microsoft Certified Professional Microsoft F372-4868
- MS: Programming in C# Microsoft F372-4870
- OCAJP7 Oracle Certified Associate, Java Programmer 7 Oracle
 OC1235467
- OCPJP7 Oracle Certified Professional, Java Programmer 7 Oracle OC 1235467
- OCEJPAD Oracle Certified Expert Java Persistence API EE 6 Oracle
 OC1235467
- OCEJSFD Oracle Certified Expert JavaServerFaces EE 6 Oracle
 OC1235467
- Mongo DB Certified Developer Associate Level MongoDB 994-208-317
- MongoDB Certified Database Administrator MongoDB 371-424-755
- Qing Certified Engineer at Level 2 ICT Systems Design FOIM (Fondazione dell'Ordine degli Ingegneri della Provincia di Milano)
 A21393c
- Honor Code Certificate for Tackling the Challenges of Big Data (February 3, 2015 March 17, 2015) MIT Professional Education
- SDLPEMT SDL Post-Editing Machine Translation Certification SDL 73681

- edX Verified Certificate for Introduction to Big Data with Apache Spark University of California, Berkeley
- edX Verified Certificate for Scalable Machine Learning University of California, Berkeley
- Berkeley XSeries Big Data University of California, Berkeley
- Gordon Effectiveness Training Effective Communication IACP Istituto del'Approccio Centrato sulla Persona
- Duke Data Analysis and Statistical Inference Duke University
 D8Z6R8SAEE
- Oracle Certified Professional Java SE 8 Oracle
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure 2018 Certified Architect Associate Oracle
- Certified Kubernetes Application Developer Cloud Native Computing Foundation (CNCF)

 CKAD-1900-0706-0100
- Google Cloud Certified Professional Cloud Architect Google 13627447
- Google Cloud Certified Professional Cloud Developer Google
 14400939
- Mulesoft Certified Developer Level 1 (Mule 4) MuleSoft e8db3255-9673-33f4-bceb-8e0e57696e25
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure 2020 Certified Developer Associate Oracle
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure 2019 Certified Architect Associate Oracle e875c103-2363-45c9-a9e2-a42530177e52
- Oracle Cloud Infrastructure 2019 Certified Architect Professional Oracle
- Mulesoft Certified Integration Architect MuleSoft

- Mulesoft Certified Platform Architect MuleSoft
- ISTQB® Certified Tester Foundation Level ISTQB® International Software
 Testing Qualifications Board
 21-CTFL-188535-12
- WSO2 Certified API Manager 4.0.0 WSO2
 L7QWL6
- MuleSoft Certified Developer Level 2 (Mule 4) MuleSoft
- Terraform Associate HashiCorp 752195b6-b795-427f-8901-6c18dae82bdc
- Salesforce Certified Hyperautomation Specialist with MuleSoft Salesforce

Skills

UML • Software Engineering • Java • Scrum • Agile Project Management • Agile Methodologies •
 SOA • Object Oriented Design • Software Design • Computer Graphics

Honors & Awards

Best Of the Web 2000 - Museums & Web

Mar 2000

Award for the WebTalk system I designed and used for the "Virtual Leonardo Project", the first 3D Collaborative Museum, hosted for several years on the web site of Milan's Science Museum

Rotary Honorable Project for the Disabled - Rotary Club Como Baradello Aug 2009

A Mention for the results obtained in the Autonomamente Project, a configurable system for remote domotic motoring of apartments for cognitively impaired people